<appendix id="hs.web" revision="alpha">
  <title>Web site and comment system usage and policies</title>

  <para id="x_OK">Thank you for your interest in commenting on our book!  We are
    excited to have made it possible for you, our readers, to submit
    comments at the level of detail of every single paragraph and code
    example.  Please feel welcome to make liberal use of the
    commenting system; we want to produce the best book we can.  (Yes,
    your use of the comment system is subject to our User Agreement;
    see <xref linkend="hs.web.useragreement"/> for details.)</para>

  <warning>
    <title>We require Javascript</title>

    <para id="x_PK">Our comment system uses Javascript extensively.  If you
      don't have Javascript enabled in your browser, you won't even
      see a hint of the existence of the comment system.
      Unfortunately, we don't have the time to spare to write a
      Javascript-free alternative.  Patches welcome!</para>
  </warning>

  <sect1 id="hs.web.comment">
    <title>Using the comment system</title>

    <para id="x_QK">Every paragraph ends with an unobtrusive anchor. When you
      click on it, it reveals the comments submitted by other readers.
      Click on the anchor again to hide the comments.</para>

    <para id="x_RK">At the end of each list of comments sits a small form where
      you can enter comments of your own.  We ask for just one piece
      of information in addition to your comment, which is your name.
      You're also welcome to provide a URL for your home page, blog,
      or what have you.</para>
    
    <sect2 id="hs.web.comment.name">
      <title>Why do we want your name?</title>

      <para id="x_SK">We'd love to credit people who give particularly good
	feedback, and to do that, we need to know who to thank. You
	don't <emphasis>have</emphasis> to give us your real name, but
	if you don't, we can't credit you, no matter how helpful you
	may be.</para>

      <note>
	<title>We can't spam you, nor can anyone else</title>

	<para id="x_TK">Notice that we don't ask for your email address?
	  Nobody's going to spam you as a result of commenting on the
	  book (unless for some reason you explicitly enter your email
	  address somewhere).</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.web.feed">
    <title>Subscribing to feeds</title>

    <para id="x_UK">Our comment system isn't just a dead dump for snippets of
      text; it's a <emphasis>conversation</emphasis> between us and
      you.  You'll notice that you can subscribe to an Atom feed for
      each web page, letting you see the latest comments, and there's
      also a feed for the book as a whole.  Each comment published
      through the feed comes with a link that lets you see that
      comment in context, and respond to it.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.web.useragreement">
    <title>User Agreement</title>

    <para id="x_VK">The following User Agreement (<quote>Agreement</quote>)
      governs the use of all <code>realworldhaskell.org</code> sites
      (<quote>Site</quote>, <quote>Sites</quote>), including without
      limitation participation in their comment systems, forums,
      chats, and all other areas (except to the extent stated
      otherwise on a specific page) as provided by the authors and
      publishers of <quote>Real World Haskell</quote>
      (<quote>us</quote> <quote>we</quote>, or
      <quote>our</quote>).</para>

    <para id="x_WK">Please read the rules contained in this agreement carefully.
      Your use of and/or registration on any aspect of this Site will
      constitute your agreement to comply with these rules. If you
      cannot agree with these rules, please do not use the
      Site.</para>

    <sect2 id="hs.web.useragreement.use">
      <title>Your use of our services</title>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para id="x_XK">Unless otherwise specified, the Site is intended for
	    your personal use only. You may not authorize others to
	    use the Site, and you are responsible for all use of the
	    Site by you and by those you allow to use, or provide
	    access to, the Site.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para id="x_YK">The Site contains material that is protected by
	    state, national and international copyright, trademark and
	    other intellectual property laws. You may not modify,
	    copy, reproduce, republish, upload, post, transmit or
	    distribute in any way any material, including code and
	    software, from the Site. You may download material from
	    the Site and may use the Site for your personal use
	    only, provided you keep intact all copyright and other
	    proprietary notices.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para id="x_ZK">The Site is not intended for users under the age of
	    13, and We do not knowingly collect personally
	    identifiable information from users under the age of 13.
	    Such users are expressly prohibited from submitting their
	    personally identifiable information to us, and from using
	    our forums and comment systems; any information submitted
	    by such users will not knowingly be used, posted, or
	    retained by us.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para id="x_aK">You agree not to place on the Site any material
	    that is abusive, harassing, racist, or hateful. Further,
	    you may not place on the Site any material that is
	    encrypted, constitutes junk mail or unauthorized
	    advertising, or commercial offers, invades anyone's
	    privacy, or encourages conduct that would constitute a
	    criminal offense, give rise to civil liability, or that
	    otherwise violates any local, state, federal, national or
	    international law or regulation. You agree to use the
	    Site only for lawful purposes and you acknowledge that
	    your failure to do so may subject you to civil and
	    criminal liability.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para id="x_bK">You are responsible for ensuring that any material you
	    provide to the Site or post on a bulletin board or
	    forum or elsewhere, including but not limited to text,
	    photographs and sound, does not violate the copyright,
	    trademark, trade secret or any other personal or
	    proprietary rights of any third party or is posted with
	    the permission of the owner(s) of such rights.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para id="x_cK">The content, organization, graphics, text, images,
	    video, design, compilation, advertising and all other
	    material on the Site, including without limitation, the
	    <quote>look and feel</quote> of this Site, are protected
	    under applicable copyrights and other proprietary
	    (including but not limited to intellectual property)
	    rights and are the property of us or our licensors. The
	    copying, rearrangement, redistribution, modification, use
	    or publication by you, directly or indirectly, of any such
	    matters or any part of the Site, including but not limited
	    to the removal or alteration of advertising, except for
	    the limited rights of use granted hereunder, is strictly
	    prohibited.</para>

	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>The text of this book and its accompanying
		graphics (except those outlined below) are licensed
		under a <ulink
		  url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">Creative 
		  Commons Attribution-Noncommercial 3.0
		  License</ulink>.</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>The 48x48 callout icons, and the RSS icon, used on
		this web site were designed by <ulink
		  url="http://mattahan.googlepages.com/">Paul
		  Davey</ulink>, and are licensed under a <ulink
		  url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.5/">Creative 
		  Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 2.5
		  License</ulink>.  Their reproduction here is with
		the permission of the author.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
  
	<listitem>
	  <para id="x_dK">You may not in any way make commercial or other
	    unauthorized use, by publication, re-transmission,
	    distribution, performance, caching, or otherwise, of
	    material obtained through the Site, except as permitted by
	    the Copyright Act or other law or as expressly permitted
	    in writing by this Agreement, Us, or the Site.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para id="x_eK">You agree not to disrupt, overwhelm, attack, modify or
	    interfere with the Site or its associated software,
	    hardware and/or servers in any way, and you agree not to
	    impede or interfere with others' use of the Site. You
	    further agree not to alter or tamper with any information
	    or materials on or associated with the Site.</para>
	</listitem>
  
	<listitem>
	  <para id="x_fK">Other than connecting to Our servers using a Web
	    browser, you may not attempt to gain access to Our servers
	    by any means - including, without limitation, by using
	    administrator passwords or by masquerading as an
	    administrator while using the Site or otherwise.</para>
	</listitem>
      
	<listitem>
	  <para id="x_gK">You acknowledge that We have not reviewed and do not
	    endorse the content of sites linked to from this Site and
	    are not responsible for the content or actions of any
	    other sites linked to from this Site. Your linking to any
	    service or site is at your sole risk.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="hs.web.useragreement.endorse">
      <title>We do not endorse anyone's comments</title>

      <para id="x_hK">We do not necessarily endorse, support, sanction,
	encourage, verify, or agree with the comments, opinions, or
	statements posted on forums, blogs or otherwise contained in
	the Site. Any information or material placed online, including
	advice and opinions, are the views and responsibility of those
	who post the statements and do not necessarily represent our
	views or those of our third party service providers.</para>

      <para id="x_iK">You agree that we and our third party service providers
	are not responsible, and shall have no liability to you, with
	respect to any information or materials posted by others,
	including defamatory, offensive or illicit material, even
	material that violates this Agreement.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="hs.web.useragreement.ownership">
      <title>Comment ownership and licensing</title>

      <para id="x_jK">You retain ownership of, and copyright on, your own
	comments.  You agree that by posting messages, uploading
	files, inputting data, or engaging in any other form of
	communication with or through the Site, you grant Us a
	royalty-free, perpetual, non-exclusive, unrestricted,
	worldwide license to use, reproduce, modify, adapt, translate,
	enhance, transmit, distribute, publicly perform, display, or
	sublicense any such communication in any medium (now in
	existence or hereinafter developed) and for any purpose,
	including commercial purposes, and to authorize others to do
	so.</para>

      <para id="x_kK">In addition, be aware that information you disclose in
	publicly accessible portions of the Site will be available
	to all users of the Site, so you should be mindful of
	personal information and other content you may wish to
	post.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="hs.web.useragreement.sales">
      <title>Merchandise sold on or through the Site</title>

      <para id="x_lK">Neither We nor our third party service providers make any
	warranties with respect to any of the merchandise, products,
	and/or services featured, mentioned, or sold by others on or
	through the Site. Transactions for any such item shall be
	between the user and the third party seller, without any
	involvement of us or our third party service
	providers. You agree that We and our third party service
	providers are not responsible, and shall have no liability to
	you, with respect to merchandise, products, and/or services
	featured, mentioned, or sold by others on or through the Site,
	including illegal, offensive or illicit items, even items that
	violates this Agreement.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="hs.web.useragreement.indemnify">
      <title>Indemnification</title>

      <para id="x_mK">You agree to indemnify Us and our affiliates, employees,
	agents, representatives and third party service providers, and
	to defend and hold each of them harmless, from any and all
	claims and liabilities (including attorneys fees) which may
	arise from your submissions, from your unauthorized use of
	material obtained through the Site, or from your breach of
	this Agreement, or from any such acts through your use of the
	Site.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="hs.web.useragreement.edit">
      <title>Response, deletion, and editing</title>

      <para id="x_nK">We reserve the right, but undertake no duty, to review,
	respond to, edit, move or delete any material provided for
	display or placed on the Site or its comment systems, in our
	sole discretion, without notice.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="hs.web.useragreement.disclaimer">
      <title>Disclaimer of warranty and limitation of
	liability</title>

      <para id="x_oK"><emphasis>You acknowledge that you are using the Site at
	  your own risk. The Site is provided <quote>as is</quote>,
	  and we, our affiliates and our third party service providers
	  hereby expressly disclaim any and all warranties, express
	  and implied, including but not limited to any warranties of
	  accuracy, reliability, title, merchantability,
	  non-infringement, fitness for a particular purpose or any
	  other warranty, condition, guarantee or representation,
	  whether oral, in writing or in electronic form, including
	  but not limited to the accuracy or completeness of any
	  information contained therein or provided by the Site. We,
	  our affiliates, and our third party service providers do not
	  represent or warrant that access to the Site will be
	  uninterrupted or that there will be no failures, errors or
	  omissions or loss of transmitted information, or that no
	  viruses will be transmitted on the Site.</emphasis></para>

      <para id="x_pK"><emphasis>We, our affiliates and our third
	  party service providers shall not be liable to you or any
	  third parties for any direct, indirect, special,
	  consequential or punitive damages allegedly sustained
	  arising out of this Agreement, the providing of the Site
	  hereunder, the sale or purchase of any goods or merchandise,
	  your access to or inability to access the Site, including
	  for viruses alleged to have been obtained from the Site,
	  your use of or reliance on the Site or any of the
	  merchandise, information or materials available on the
	  Site, regardless of the type of claim or the nature of
	  the cause of action, even if advised of the possibility of
	  such damages. Some states do not allow the exclusion of
	  implied warranties or the limitation or exclusion of
	  liability for incidental or consequential damages, so the
	  above exclusions or limitations may not apply to you. You
	  may also have other rights that vary from state to
	  state.</emphasis></para>

      <para id="x_qK"><emphasis>You hereby agree to release us, our affiliates
	  and third-party service providers, and each of their
	  respective directors, officers, employees, and agents from
	  claims, demands and damages (actual and consequential) of
	  every kind and nature, known and unknown, suspected and
	  unsuspected, disclosed and undisclosed
	  (<quote>claims</quote>), arising out of or in any way
	  connected with your use of this site. If you are a
	  California resident, you waive California Civil Code Section
	  1542, which states, in part: <quote>A general release does
	    not extend to claims which the creditor does not know or
	    suspect to exist in his favor at the time of executing the
	    release, which if known by him must have materially
	    affected his settlement with the
	    debtor</quote>.</emphasis></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</appendix>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("00book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
