<!-- vim: set filetype=docbkxml shiftwidth=2 autoindent expandtab tw=77 : -->

<chapter id="hs.funcstypes">
  <title>Types and Functions</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Haskell's type system</title>
    
    <para><quote>Haskell has a strong, static type system with
	inference.</quote> For a short sentence, this one has a lot
      for us to pore over.  Because Haskell is quite different from
      mainstream programming languages in how it treats types, let's
      not assume anything as we talk about types.</para>

    <para>Every value and expression in Haskell has a
      <emphasis>type</emphasis>.  The type of a value indicates that
      it shares certain properties with other values that have the
      same type.  (You'll see us refer to a value <quote>having the
	type <code>X</code></quote>, or <quote>being of type
	<code>X</code></quote>.  The two phrases mean the same thing.)
      All values that have the type <type>Integer</type> have the
      ability to be added to other values of type
      <type>Integer</type>, and so on.</para>

    <para>Haskell has a <quote>strong</quote> type system, in which
      every expression and value has exactly one type.  Another aspect
      of Haskell's view of strong typing is that it will not
      automatically convert values from one type to another, a feature
      present in some other languages.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Conversations about type systems can lead to many a
	misunderstanding among programmers.  Some people say that C
	has a strong type system; others claim that Python does.
	Haskell programmers think strong typing is still something
	else.</para>

      <para>Since there's no universally agreed upon meaning for the
	phrase <quote>strong type</quote>,  it's best not to assume
	that someone else shares the same notion of it as you do.  (We
	also suggest that putting forth one definition as better than
	another doesn't often lead to enlightened discussion.)</para>
    </note>

    <para>Having a <quote>static</quote> type system means that the
      compiler knows the type of every value and expression at compile
      time, before any code is ever executed.  A Haskell compiler or
      interpreter will detect when we try to use types inconsistently
      in our code, and reject the code with an error message.</para>

    &ch03.basics.ghci:error;

    <para>Haskell's combination of strong and static typing also makes
      it impossible for type errors to occur at runtime.</para>

    <para>Finally, <quote>type inference</quote> means what it says:
      the compiler can automatically figure out the types of most
      values for us, so that we don't have to explicitly label
      them.</para>

    <para>We've already briefly seen Haskell's notation for types in
      <xref linkend="hs.starting.types"/>.  We write <code>expression
	:: <type>MyType</type></code> to say that
      <code>expression</code> has the type <type>MyType</type>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Some common basic types</title>
    
    <para>We've already encountered a few types in <xref
	linkend="hs.starting.types"/>.  Haskell has a number of
      built-in types that we'll use over and over.  Here are some of
      the language's basic types, types that aren't composed of other
      types</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>The <type>Char</type> type represents a character. The
	  values of <type>Char</type> are drawn from the Unicode
	  character set.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>The <type>Bool</type> type represents a value in Boolean
	  logic.  The possible values of <type>Bool</type> are
	  <code>True</code> and <code>False</code>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>The <type>Int</type> type represents a signed,
	  fixed-width integer.  The exact range of values represented
	  by <type>Int</type> depends on the system's longest
	  <quote>native</quote> integer: on a 32-bit machine, an
	  <type>Int</type> is usually 32 bits wide, while on a 64-bit
	  machine, it is usually 64 bits wide.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>The <type>Integer</type> type represents a signed
	  integer of arbitrary width.  <type>Integer</type> values are
	  not used as often as <type>Int</type>s, because they're a
	  lot more expensive to work with.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>The <type>Double</type> type is the type usually used to
	  represent floating point numbers.  It is typically 64 bits
	  wide, and uses the machine's native floating point
	  representation.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Useful composite data types: lists and tuples</title>

    <para>The most common composite data types in Haskell are the list
      and tuple.</para>

    <para>We've already seen the list type mentioned in <xref
	linkend="hs.starting.string"/>, where we found that Haskell
      represents a text string as a list of <type>Char</type> values,
      and that the type <quote>list of <type>Char</type></quote> is
      written <type>[Char]</type>.</para>

    <para>More generally, we can write the type <quote>list of
	<varname role="type">a</varname></quote> for any type <varname
	role="type">a</varname> by enclosing <varname
	role="type">a</varname> in square brackets, <type>[a]</type>.
      Lists are strongly typed: a list of one type has an identity of
      its own, distinct from a list of another type. The type
      <type>[Int]</type> is a list that can only contain values of
      type <type>Int</type>, for example.</para>

    <para>A tuple is a fixed-size collection of values, each of which
      can be of any type.  Unlike a list, the elements of which must
      all have the same type, there's no need for the elements of a
      tuple to be related.  We write a tuple by enclosing its elements
      in parentheses and separating them with commas.  We use the same
      notation for writing its type.</para>

    &tuple.ghci:tuple;

    <para>We can construct a tuple with any number of elements
      (although in practice, a tuple with more than a handful becomes
      unwieldy).  A tuple's type encodes the number and types of its
      elements in its own type, so tuples containing different numbers
      or types of elements have different types of their own.</para>

    &tuple.ghci:type;
    
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Defining a new data type</title>
      
    <para>We introduce a new data type using the <code>data</code>
      keyword.</para>

    &MyType.hs:MyType;

    <para>The <type>MyType</type> after the <code>data</code> keyword
      is the name of our new type.  (As we've already mentioned, a
      type name must start with a capital letter.)  The string
      <code>MyConstructor</code> is the name of the
      <emphasis>constructor</emphasis> we'll call to create a value of
      this type.  (As with a type name, a constructor name must start
      with a capital letter.)  Finally, the <type>Int</type> and
      <type>String</type> are the <emphasis>components</emphasis> of
      the type.  A component serves the same purpose in Haskell as a
      field in a structure or class would in another language.</para>

    <note>
      <para>We'll explain the full meaning of <code>deriving
	  (Show)</code> later, in
	<xref linkend="hs.typeclasses.wellknown.show"/>.  For now,
	it's enough to know that we need to tack this onto a type
	declaration so that &ghci; will automatically know how to
	print a value of this type.</para>
    </note>

    <para>We can create a new value of type <type>MyType</type> by
      treating <function>MyConstructor</function> as a function, and
      calling it with arguments of types <type>Int</type> and
      <type>String</type>.</para>

    &MyType.hs:myValue;

    <para>Once we've defined a type, we can experiment with it in
      &ghci;, starting by using the <command>:load</command> command
      to load our source file.</para>

    &mytype.ghci:load;

    <para>Remember the <code>myValue</code> variable we defined?  Here
      it is.</para>

    &mytype.ghci:myValue;

    <para>We can construct new values interactively in &ghci;,
      too.</para>

    &mytype.ghci:newValue;

    <para>To find out more about a type, we can use some of &ghci;'s
      browsing capabilities.  The <command>:info</command> command
      gets &ghci; to tell us us everything it knows about a
      type.</para>
    
    &mytype.ghci:info;

    <para>We can also find out why we use
      <function>MyConstructor</function> to construct a new value of
      type <type>MyType</type>.</para>

    &mytype.ghci:type;

    <para>From Haskell's perspective, then, a constructor is just
      another function, one that happens to return a value of the type
      we want to construct.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Algebraic data types</title>

    <para>The <type>Bool</type> type that we introduced earlier is the
      simplest example of a sort of type called an <emphasis>algebraic
	data type</emphasis>. An algebraic data type has a fixed set
      of possible values, each of which is identified by a distinct
      constructor.</para>

    <para>In the case of <type>Bool</type>, the type has two
      constructors, <code>True</code> and <code>False</code>.  Each
      constructor is separated by a <literal>|</literal> character,
      which we can read as <quote>or</quote>.  These are usually
      referred to as alternatives or cases.</para>

      &Bool.hs:Bool;

    <para>Each constructor can take zero or more arguments; the
      numbers and types of the arguments accepted by each constructor
      are independent.  For example, here's one way we might represent
      versions of the Windows operating system, where old releases
      were monolithic, and newer releases have <quote>service pack
	levels</quote> denoting major updates after their initial
      releases.</para>

      &OsVersion.hs:WindowsVersion;

    <para>The alternatives that represent older releases don't need
      arguments, but those for the newer releases need an
      <type>Int</type> to represent the patch level.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Analogues to algebraic data types in other
	languages</title>

      <para>Algebraic data types provide a single structuring
	mechanism in instances where other languages have several
	different building blocks.  Here are some analogues from C and
	C++, which might make it clearer what we can do with algebraic
	data types.</para>

      <para>With just one constructor, an algebraic data type groups
	related values into one, and gives that value an identity
	distinct from other types.  It corresponds to a
	<code>struct</code> in C or C++, and its components to the
	fields of a struct.</para>

      <para>If an algebraic data type has multiple alternatives, we
	can think of it as similar to a <code>union</code> in C or
	C++.  A big difference between the two is that a union doesn't
	tell us which alternative is actually present; we have to
	record which alternative we're using ourselves, usually in
	another field of a struct.  This means that unions can
	sometimes be sources of bugs, where our notion of which
	alternative we should be using is incorrect.</para>

      <para>With an algebraic data type, Haskell stores the
	constructor that we use in the value that we create, so we
	don't need to manually sock it away somewhere else.</para>

      <para>Algebraic data types also serve where we'd use an
	<code>enum</code> in C or C++, to represent a range of
	discrete symbolic values.</para>

      &Enum.hs:Roygbiv;

    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>A few final notes</title>

      <para>From reading the preceding sections, it should be clear
	that <emphasis>all</emphasis> of the data types that we define
	with the <code>data</code> keyword are algebraic data types.
	Some may have just one alternative; others have several; but
	they're all using the same organising machinery.</para>

      <para>Another useful thing to know is that it's perfectly okay
	for the name of an algebraic type to have the same name as one
	of its constructors to be the same.  It's always obvious from
	context whether we're using a name to refer to a type or a
	constructor, so this doesn't introduce any ambiguity.</para>

      <para>Giving a type and its constructor the same name is in fact
	something that we do frequently when the type has just one
	constructor.</para>

      &TypeName.hs:PerfectlyNormal;

      <para>When a type has multiple constructors, it's still legal to
	give one of the constructors the  same name as the type, but
	this is much less common.</para>

      &TypeName.hs:LegalButWeird;

    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Parameterised types</title>

    <para>In our discussion of lists, we mentioned that we can create
      a list of values of any type.  We can define our own types that
      allow this, too.  To do this, we introduce variables into a type
      declaration.</para>

      &Wrapper.hs:Wrapper;

    <para>Here, the variable <varname role="type">a</varname> is not a
      regular variable; it's called a <emphasis>type
	variable</emphasis>, because it indicates that our
      <type>Wrapper</type> type takes another type as its parameter
      (hence calling it a parameterised type). What this lets us do is
      use <type>Wrapper</type> on values of any type.</para>

      &Wrapper.hs:wrappedTypes;

    <para>As usual, we can load our source file into &ghci; and
      experiment with it.</para>

      &wrapper.ghci:experiment;

    <para><type>Wrapper</type> is a <quote>generic</quote> container
      type (albeit a fairly useless one); we can construct a
      <type>Wrapper</type> from a value of any type.  It is also
      strongly typed; the type of whatever it contains is encoded in
      its own type.</para>

    <para>To once again extend an analogy to more familiar languages,
      this gives us a facility that bears some resemblance to
      templates in C++, and to generics in Java.  (In fact, Java's
      generics facility was inspired by several aspects of Haskell's
      type system.)</para>

    <para>We can nest uses of parameterised types inside each other,
      but when we do, we may need to use parentheses to tell the
      Haskell compiler what we mean.</para>

      &Wrapper.hs:parens;
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Recursive types</title>

    <para>Here's a definition of a binary tree type.</para>

      &Tree.hs:Tree;

    <para>We call this a <emphasis>recursive</emphasis> type because
      <type>Tree</type>, the type we're defining, appears both on the
      left hand side and the right hand side of the definition: we
      define the type in terms of itself.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>A little more about lists</title>

    <para>Now that we're getting familiar with some of the jargon
      around types, we can revisit lists.  Haskell's list type is a
      parameterised type, because we can make lists of any other type.
      It is also an algebraic data type, with two constructors.  One
      is the empty list, written <code>[]</code> (sometimes pronounced
      <quote>nil</quote>, which is borrowed from Lisp).</para>

    &list.ghci:empty;

    <para>The other is the <function>(:)</function> operator, often
      pronounced <quote>cons</quote> (this is short for
      <quote>construct</quote>, and also borrowed from Lisp).  The
      <function>(:)</function> operator takes an element and a list,
      and constructs a new list.</para>

    &list.ghci:cons;

    <para>Because <function>(:)</function> constructs a list from
      another list, the list type is recursive.  So here we have a
      built-in type that's parameterised, recursive, and
      algebraic.</para>

    <para>One consequence of lists being generic is that lists of
      lists, for example, aren't special in any way.</para>

    &list.ghci:listlist;

    <para>This has type <type>[[String]]</type>, a list of lists of
      strings.  But since <type>String</type> is just a synonym for
      <type>[Char]</type>, it's <emphasis>really</emphasis> a list of
      lists of lists of <type>Char</type>.  Whew!</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Unit, the zero-element tuple</title>

    <para>Haskell has a special tuple type with no elements, written
      <type>()</type>, and pronounced <quote>unit</quote>.</para>

    &unit.ghci:unit;

    <para>This type is only really used with parameterised data types,
      to indicate that one of the type parameters isn't being used.
      Since it doesn't encode any information, it's a rough equivalent
      to <code>void</code> in C.</para>

    <para>Here's an example of <type>()</type> in use.  We can
      generalise our earlier <type>Tree</type> type a little, so that
      internal nodes contain values of type <varname
	role="type">a</varname>, while leaves contain values of type
      <varname role="type">b</varname>.</para>

    &Tree.hs:ComplexTree;

    <para>If we wanted to create a <type>ComplexTree</type> where we
      wanted to store <type>Int</type>s on the leaves, but don't care
      about the internal nodes.  We would write its type as
      <type>ComplexTree () Int</type>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.strong">
    <title>Strong and Static Typing With Inference</title>
    <remark>FIXME</remark>
    <para>See also <xref linkend="hs.funcstypes.inference"/>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.patternmatching">
    <title>Pattern Matching</title>

    <remark>FIXME: Introduce pattern matching.  Show how to write a
      function as a series of clauses, each predicated on its
      patterns.
    </remark>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.basictypes">
    <title>Basic Types</title>
    <remark>FIXME: Type basics: products (tuples), sums
      (Maybe,Either), recursive types (lists). Give us enough glue to
      pattern match on.
    </remark>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.guards">
    <title>Guards</title>
    <remark>FIXME:   Introduce guards.  Show that guards and patterns
      can be used together or independently.
    </remark>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.ifcase">
    <title>Conditionals: if and case</title>
    <remark>FIXME</remark>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.local">
    <title>Local definitions: let and where</title>
    <remark>FIXME</remark>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.recursion">
    <title>Recursion</title>
    <remark>FIXME</remark>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.rle">
    <title>Example: Run-Length Encoding</title>
    <remark>FIXME:   Example: run-length encoding.  Use to show how
      looping can be done via tail recursion.
    </remark>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.infix">
    <title>Infix Functions</title>
    <remark>FIXME:  Infix functions.  Using and defining them, and
      infix use of normal functions.
    </remark>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.inference">
    <title>Type Inference</title>
    <remark>FIXME: Discuss type inference: what it is and how it can
      save a lot of work.
    </remark>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.anonymous">
    <title>Anonymous (Lambda) Functions</title>
    <remark>FIXME</remark>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.partialapp">
    <title>Partial Application</title>
    <remark>FIXME</remark>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.typeclasses">
    <title>Typeclasses</title>
    <remark>FIXME: Introduce type classes.  Show how ghci infers types
      with constraints. Define some functions that use type class
      constraints. Talk about when it's appropriate to write explicit
      signatures. 
    </remark>
    <para>See also <xref linkend="hs.typeclasses"/>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.mapapi">
    <title>Example: Data.Map API</title>
    <remark>FIXME: Small example would be a finite map data structure
      API, with a list and tree implementation (different complexity,
      same api). Ties together basic types, small functions, top level
      functions. class Map m where new     :: m k v insert  :: k -> v
      -> m k v -> m k v lookup  :: k -> m k v -> v -- simple, O(n)
      data Map1 k v = [(k,v)] -- less simple, O(log n) data Map2 k v =
      Node k v (Map2 k v) (Map2 k v) | Empty

    </remark>
  </sect1>

</chapter>
<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("00book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
