<!-- vim: set filetype=docbkxml shiftwidth=2 autoindent expandtab tw=77 : -->

<chapter id="hs.funcstypes" revision="unpublished">
  <title>Types and Functions</title>

  <para id="x_n2">Topics: built-in types.  Writing functions.  Creating new
    types.</para>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.types">
    <title>Haskell's type system</title>
    
    <para id="x_o2"><quote>Haskell has a strong, static type system with
	inference.</quote> For a short sentence, this one gives us a
      lot for us to pore over.  Because Haskell is quite different
      from mainstream programming languages in how it treats types,
      let's not assume too much shared understanding as we talk about
      types.</para>

    <para id="x_p2">Every value and expression in Haskell has a
      <emphasis>type</emphasis>.  The type of a value indicates that
      it shares certain properties with other values that have the
      same type.  (You'll see us refer to a value <quote>having the
	type <code>X</code></quote>, or <quote>being of type
	<code>X</code></quote>.  The two phrases mean the same thing.)
      All values that have the type <type>Integer</type> have the
      ability to be added to other values of type
      <type>Integer</type>, and so on.</para>

    <para id="x_q2">Haskell has a <quote>strong</quote> type system, in which
      every expression and value has exactly one type.  Another aspect
      of Haskell's view of strong typing is that it will not
      automatically convert values from one type to another, a feature
      present in some other languages.</para>

    <note>
      <para id="x_r2">Conversations about type systems can lead to many a
	misunderstanding among programmers.  Some people say that C
	has a strong type system; others claim that Python does.
	Haskell programmers think strong typing is still something
	else.</para>

      <para id="x_s2">Since there's no universally agreed upon meaning for the
	phrase <quote>strong type</quote>,  it's best not to assume
	that someone else shares the same notion of it as you do.  (We
	also suggest that putting forth one definition as better than
	another doesn't often lead to enlightened discussion.)</para>
    </note>

    <para id="x_t2">Having a <quote>static</quote> type system means that the
      compiler knows the type of every value and expression at compile
      time, before any code is ever executed.  A Haskell compiler or
      interpreter will detect when we try to use types inconsistently
      in our code, and reject the code with an error message.</para>

    &ch03.basics.ghci:error;

    <para id="x_u2">Haskell's combination of strong and static typing also makes
      it impossible for type errors to occur at runtime.</para>

    <para id="x_v2">Finally, <quote>type inference</quote> means what it says:
      the compiler can automatically figure out the types of most
      values for us, so that we don't have to explicitly label
      them.</para>

    <para id="x_w2">We've already briefly seen Haskell's notation for types in
      <xref linkend="hs.starting.types"/>.  We write <code>expression
	:: <type>MyType</type></code> to say that
      <code>expression</code> has the type <type>MyType</type>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.basic">
    <title>Some common basic types</title>
    
    <para id="x_x2">We've already encountered a few types in <xref
	linkend="hs.starting.types"/>.  Haskell has a number of
      built-in types that we'll use over and over.  Here are some of
      the language's basic types, types that aren't composed of other
      types</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para id="x_y2">The <type>Char</type> type represents a character. The
	  values of <type>Char</type> are drawn from the Unicode
	  character set, which covers most of the world's written
	  languages.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para id="x_z2">The <type>Bool</type> type represents a value in Boolean
	  logic.  The possible values of <type>Bool</type> are
	  <code>True</code> and <code>False</code>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para id="x_A3">The <type>Int</type> type represents a signed,
	  fixed-width integer.  The exact range of values represented
	  by <type>Int</type> depends on the system's longest
	  <quote>native</quote> integer: on a 32-bit machine, an
	  <type>Int</type> is usually 31 bits wide, while on a 64-bit
	  machine, it is usually 63 bits wide.  (There are also
	  numeric types that are exactly 8, 16, and so on bits wide;
	  we'll get to those later.)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para id="x_B3">The <type>Integer</type> type represents a signed
	  integer of arbitrary size.  <type>Integer</type>s are not
	  used as often as <type>Int</type>s, because they're
	  more expensive to work with.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para id="x_C3">The <type>Double</type> type is the type usually used to
	  represent floating point numbers.  It is typically 64 bits
	  wide, and uses the system's native floating point
	  representation.  (A narrower type, <type>Float</type>, also
	  exists, but its use is discouraged; Haskell compiler writers
	  concentrate more on making <type>Double</type>
	  efficient, so <type>Float</type> is much slower.)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.composite">
    <title>Useful composite data types: lists and tuples</title>

    <para id="x_D3">The most common composite data types in Haskell are the list
      and tuple.</para>

    <para id="x_E3">We've already seen the list type mentioned in <xref
	linkend="hs.starting.string"/>, where we found that Haskell
      represents a text string as a list of <type>Char</type> values,
      and that the type <quote>list of <type>Char</type></quote> is
      written <type>[Char]</type>.  (The type <type>String</type> is
      simply an alias for <type>[Char]</type>.  You can use the two
      interchangeably.)</para>

    <para id="x_F3">More generally, we can write the type <quote>list of
	<varname role="type">a</varname></quote> for any type <varname
	role="type">a</varname> by enclosing <varname
	role="type">a</varname> in square brackets, <type>[a]</type>.
      Lists are strongly typed: a list of one type has an identity of
      its own, distinct from a list of another type. The type
      <type>[Int]</type> is a list that can only contain values of
      type <type>Int</type>, for example.  We also call the list type
      <emphasis>polymorphic</emphasis>, because it can contain any
      type of value.</para>

    <para id="x_G3">Lists are the <quote>bread and butter</quote> of Haskell
      collections.  Whereas in an imperative language, we might repeat
      a task over many items by iterating through a loop, this is
      something that we tend to do in Haskell by recursing over a
      list.  We'll be spending a lot more time discussing lists in
      <xref linkend="hs.fp"/>.</para>

    <para id="x_H3">A tuple is a fixed-size collection of values, each of which
      can be of any type.  Unlike a list (the elements of which must
      all have the same type), there's no need for the elements of a
      tuple to have related types.  We write a tuple by enclosing its
      elements in parentheses and separating them with commas.  We use
      the same notation for writing its type.</para>

    &tuple.ghci:tuple;

    <para id="x_I3">We can construct a tuple with any number of elements
      (although in practice, a tuple with more than a handful becomes
      unwieldy).  A tuple's type encodes the number and types of its
      elements in its own type.  This means that tuples containing
      different numbers or types of elements have distinct types of
      their own.</para>

    &tuple.ghci:type;

    <para id="x_J3">A two-tuple of an <type>Int</type> and a <type>String</type>
      has a different type than a two-tuple of a <type>Bool</type> and
      a <type>Bool</type>, for example, and a three-tuple has a
      different type than a four-tuple.</para>

    <para id="x_K3">Probably the most common use of tuples is to let us return
      multiple values from a function.  We can also use them in other
      places where we want a fixed-size collection of values, for
      which the kind of container we're using isn't of much
      importance.  An example of this might be to represent a row in
      the result of a a database query.</para>

    <para>A handy rule of thumb for remembering which is which is that
      a list has variable size and elements of uniform type, while a
      tuple has a uniform size and elements of variable type.</para>

    <sect2 id="hs.funcstypes.composite.exercises">
      <title>Exercises</title>

      <qandaset defaultlabel="number">
	<qandaentry>
	  <question>
	    <para id="x_L3">What are the types of the following
	      expressions?</para>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para id="x_M3"><code>False</code></para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para id="x_N3"><code>(["foo", "bar"], 'a')</code></para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para id="x_O3"><code>[(True, []), (False, [['a']])]</code></para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </question>
	</qandaentry>
      </qandaset>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.calling">
    <title>Calling functions</title>

    <para id="x_P3">Now that we've had our fill of data types for a while, let's
      turn our attention to <emphasis>working</emphasis> with some of
      the types we've seen.  We've already seen how to perform
      arithmetic in <xref linkend="hs.starting.calc.arithmetic"/>, and it
      looks quite as it does in other languages.</para>

    <para id="x_Q3">However, our discussion of lists and tuples mentioned how we
      can construct them, but not how we do anything with them
      afterwards.  Haskell defines a large library of functions for
      working with lists and (to a lesser extent) tuples, so let's
      find out how to use a few of those functions.</para>

    <para id="x_R3">To call a function in Haskell, we provide the name of the
      function followed by its arguments, all separated by white space.
      As an example, let's call the <function>head</function>
      function, which returns the first element of a list.</para>

    &func.ghci:head;

    <para id="x_S3">Its counterpart, <function>tail</function>, returns all
      <emphasis>but</emphasis> the head of a list.</para>

    &func.ghci:tail;

    <para id="x_T3">A related pair of functions, <function>take</function> and
      <function>drop</function>, take two arguments: given a number
      and a list, they return either the first, or all but the first,
      number of elements of the list.  (Here, remember that a
      <type>String</type> is a list of <type>Char</type>.)</para>

    &func.ghci:takeDrop;

    <para id="x_U3">If you're used to function call syntax in other languages,
      this notation can take a little getting used to, but it's
      undeniably simple and uniform.  Here's what we mean by
      uniform.</para>

    &func.ghci:snd;

    <para id="x_V3">In some other languages, the call to
      <function>snd</function> above might mean <quote>call
	<function>snd</function> with two arguments,
	<literal>1</literal> and <literal>2</literal></quote>, but in
      Haskell, it's a single-argument call, passing the tuple
      <literal>(1,2)</literal>.</para>

    <para id="x_W3">By the way, <function>snd</function> has a companion
      function, <function>fst</function>, which returns the first
      element of a tuple.</para>

    &func.ghci:fst;

    <sect2 id="hs.funcstypes.calling.expr">
      <title>Passing an expression to a function</title>

      <para id="x_X3">Haskell evaluates an expression from left to right.  If we
	want to use the result of one expression as an argument to
	another, we have to keep this in mind and use parentheses to
	tell the parser what we really mean.  Here's an
	example.</para>

      &func.ghci:headDrop;

      <para id="x_Y3">We can read this as <quote>pass the result of the
	  expression <code>drop 4 "azerty"</code> as the argument to
	  <function>head</function></quote>.  If we were to leave out
	the parentheses, Haskell would instead interpret the
	expression as <quote>pass <function>drop</function> as the
	  argument to <function>head</function></quote>.  Compilation
	would fail with a type error, as <function>drop</function> is
	a function, not a list.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.sigs">
    <title>Understanding a function's type signature</title>

    <para id="x_Z3">A consequence of Haskell's strong typing is that
      <function>fst</function> and <function>snd</function> only
      accept two-tuples as arguments.  Let's see what &ghci; tells us
      about their types.</para>

    &func.ghci:fst.type;

    <para id="x_a3">We can read the <literal>-&gt;</literal> above as
      <quote>returns</quote>.  The entire signature thus tells us that
      <function>fst</function> takes any two-tuple whose elements are
      of types <varname role="type">a</varname> and <varname
	role="type">b</varname> (each of which can be of any type),
      and returns a value with type <varname role="type">a</varname>.
      Sure enough, if we try calling <function>fst</function> with a
      three-tuple, things don't go so well.</para>

    &func.ghci:fst.bad;

    <para id="x_b3">Notice that the type signatures above give us a strong hint
      as to what these functions might actually
      <emphasis>do</emphasis>. This is an incredibly valuable property
      of types in a functional language.  Since there aren't usually
      any side effects for us to worry about, figuring what a function
      does can often be a matter of reading its name and understanding
      its type signature, with no <quote>regular documentation</quote>
      required.</para>

    <para id="x_c3">Just as we called the list type polymorphic because it can
      contain values of any type, when a function has type variables
      in its signature, indicating that some of its arguments can be
      of any type, we call the function polymorphic, too.</para>

    <para id="x_d3">So far, we haven't seen a signature for a function that
      takes <emphasis>more</emphasis> than one argument.  We've
      already encountered a few such functions; let's look at
      <function>take</function>.</para>

    &func.ghci:take.type;

    <para id="x_e3">It's pretty clear that there's something going on with an
      <type>Int</type> and some lists, but why are there two
      <literal>-&gt;</literal> symbols in the signature?  Haskell
      parses this chain of arrows from right to left.  If we introduce
      parentheses, it makes it clearer how Haskell is interpreting
      this type signature.</para>

    &Take.hs:type;

    <para id="x_f3">From this, it looks like we ought to read the type signature
      as a function that takes one argument, an <type>Int</type>, and
      returns another function.  That other function also takes one
      argument, a list, and returns a list of the same type as its
      argument.</para>

    <para id="x_g3">This is an intriguing idea, but it's not easy to see just
      yet what its consequences might be.  We'll return to this topic
      in <xref linkend="hs.fp.partialapp"/>, once we've spent a bit of
      time writing functions.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.srcfile">
    <title>Haskell source files, and writing simple functions</title>

    <para id="x_h3">Now that we know how to call functions, it's time we turned
      our attention to writing them.  While we can write functions in
      &ghci;, it's not a good environment for doing so, because it
      limits any expression or definition to one line in length.  So
      instead, we'll finally break down and create a source
      file.</para>

    <para id="x_i3">Haskell source files are usually identified with a suffix of
      <filename>.hs</filename>.  Here's a simple function definition:
      open up a file named <filename>add.hs</filename>, and add these
      contents to it.</para>

    &add.hs:add;

    <para id="x_j3">On the left hand side of the <literal>=</literal> is the
      name of the function, followed by the arguments to the function.
      On the right hand side is the body of the function.  With our
      source file saved, we can load it into &ghci;, and use our new
      <function>add</function> function straight away.</para>

    &add.ghci:add;

    <para id="x_k3">When we call <function>add</function>, the variables
      <varname>a</varname> and <varname>b</varname> on the left hand
      side of our definition are given (or <quote>bound to</quote>)
      the values <literal>1</literal> and <literal>2</literal>, then
      the right hand side is evaluated, and the result
      returned.</para>

    <para id="x_l3">Haskell doesn't need a <command>return</command> statement;
      the result of a function is the result of evaluating whatever
      expression is in the function's body.</para>

    <sect2 id="hs.funcstypes.variable">
      <title>Just what is a variable, anyway?</title>

      <para id="x_rK">If you're used to imperative programming languages, you're
	likely to think of a variable as a way of identifying a
	<quote>box</quote>.  You can get the value that's currently in
	a box, and you can change the value in the box using
	assignment.</para>

      <para id="x_sK">In Haskell, a variable is the name of a
	<emphasis>value</emphasis>.  This is critically different from
	the name of a box: we're used to being able to change what's
	inside a box from our dealings with other languages, but we
	can't change the <quote>twoness</quote> of the value
	<literal>2</literal>.</para>

      <para id="x_tK">Creating a variable in Haskell just gives a convenient
	name to a value; we can't change the value associated with a
	variable.  This bears a strong similarity to the way we think
	about variables in mathematics.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="hs.funcstypes.if">
      <title>Conditional evaluation</title>

      <para id="x_m3">Like other languages, Haskell has an <code>if</code>
	expression.  Let's see it in action, then we'll explain what's
	going on.  As an example, we'll write our own version of the
	standard <function>take</function> function. Before we begin,
	let's probe a little bit of how <function>take</function>
	behaves, so we can replicate its behaviour.</para>

      &myTake.ghci:take;

      <para id="x_n3">From the above, it seems that <function>take</function>
	returns the original list if the number to remove is greater than
	the number of elements, and that it treats negative numbers as
	zero.  Here's a <function>myTake</function> function that has
	the same behaviour, and uses Haskell's <code>if</code>
	expression to decide what to do.</para>

      &myTake.hs:myTake;

      <para>The <code>then</code> arm of the <code>if</code>
	expression returns the input list once either the number of
	elements to remove reaches zero or the current list is empty.
	The <code>else</code> arm calls <function>myTake</function>
	recursively, decrementing the counter and stripping one
	element from the front of the list.  The conditional clause
	inside the <code>if</code> causes the <code>else</code> branch
	to be called repeatedly until either the remaining list is
	empty or there are no elements left to return.</para>

      <para id="x_o3">Let's save it in a file named
	<filename>myTake.hs</filename>, then load it into
	&ghci;.</para>

      &myTake.ghci:myTake;

      <para id="x_p3">Now that we've seen <function>myTake</function> in action,
	let's return to the source code and look at a few of the
	novelties we've introduced.</para>

      <para id="x_q3">First is the <code>if</code> keyword itself.  It takes an
	expression of type <type>Bool</type>.  If that evaluates to
	<function>True</function>, it evaluates the expression on the
	<code>then</code> branch.  Otherwise, it evaluates the
	expression on the <code>else</code> branch.</para>

      <para id="x_r3">The combination of <code>if</code>, <code>then</code>,
	<code>else</code> and the expression after each keyword
	combine to make up a single expression, as far as Haskell is
	concerned.  Whichever branch is evaluated is the result of the
	<code>if</code>.  Because an expression can only have one
	type, the expressions in the <code>then</code> and
	<code>else</code> branches must have the same type.  If they
	don't, an <code>if</code> expression won't typecheck.</para>

      <para id="x_s3">Whereas it can make sense in an imperative language to
	omit the <code>else</code> branch from an <code>if</code>,
	this would be nonsensical in Haskell.  An <code>if</code>
	expression that was missing an <code>else</code> wouldn't have
	a value if the condition after the <code>if</code> evaluated
	to <function>False</function>, so it couldn't typecheck.</para>

      <para id="x_t3">The second novelty is almost trivial: the
	<function>null</function> function, which we use in the
	Boolean portion of the <code>if</code>, indicates whether a
	list is empty.</para>

      &myTake.ghci:null;

      <para id="x_u3">Third is that our function calls itself recursively.  This
	is an early example of how, in Haskell, we use recursion where
	in an imperative language we'd probably use a loop.</para>

      <para id="x_v3">Finally, our <code>if</code> expression spans several
	lines.  We line the <code>then</code> and <code>else</code>
	branches up under the <code>if</code> for neatness, but this
	is not mandatory.  We could put all of them on a single line,
	for example, but we'd end up with less readable code.</para>

      &myTake.hs:myTake2;

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="hs.funcstypes.error">
      <title>Reporting errors</title>

      <para id="x_w3">Haskell provides a standard function, <function>error ::
	  Char -&gt; a</function>, that we can call when something has
	gone terribly wrong in our code.  We give it a string
	parameter, which is the error message to display.  Its type
	signature looks peculiar; how can it produce a value of any
	type <varname role="type">a</varname> given just a string? The
	answer is that it doesn't, because <function>error</function>
	is special.</para>

      <para id="x_x3">It has that type so that we can call it anywhere and it
	will always have the right type.   However, instead of
	returning a value like a normal function, it immediately
	terminates evaluation, and prints the error message we give
	it.  Here's an example.  The <function>mySecond</function>
	function returns the second element of its input list, but
	fails if its input list isn't long enough.</para>

      &MySecond.hs:mySecond;

      <para id="x_y3">As usual, we can see how this works in practice in
	&ghci;.</para>

      &error.ghci:mySecond;

      <para id="x_z3">Notice that in the third case above, where we're trying to
	use the result of the call to <function>mySecond</function> as
	the argument to another function, evaluation still terminates
	and drops us back to the &ghci; prompt.  This is both the
	strength and weakness calling <function>error</function>: it
	doesn't let us distinguish between recoverable errors and
	problems so severe that they really should terminate a
	program.  We'll see one way around this problem in
	<xref linkend="hs.funcstypes.maybe"/>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="hs.funcstypes.sigs.exercises">
      <title>Exercises</title>

      <qandaset defaultlabel="number">
	<qandaentry>
	  <question>
	    <para id="x_A4">Haskell provides a standard function, <code>last ::
		[a] -&gt; a</code>, that returns the last element of a
	      list.  Write a function <function>lastButOne</function>,
	      that returns the element <emphasis>before</emphasis>
	      the last.</para>
	  </question>
	</qandaentry>

	<qandaentry>
	  <question>
	    <para id="x_B4">Load your <function>lastButOne</function> function
	      into &ghci;, and try it out on lists of different
	      lengths.  What happens when you pass it a list that's
	      too short?</para>
	  </question>
	</qandaentry>
      </qandaset>

    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.data">
    <title>Defining a new data type</title>
      
    <para id="x_C4">Although lists and tuples are useful, we'll still often want
      to construct new data types of our own.  We define a new data
      type using the <code>data</code> keyword.</para>

    &MyType.hs:MyType;

    <para id="x_D4">The <type>MyType</type> after the <code>data</code> keyword
      is the name of our new type.  (As we've already mentioned, a
      type name must start with a capital letter.)  The string
      <code>MyConstructor</code> is the name of the
      <emphasis>constructor</emphasis> we'll call to create a value of
      this type.  (As with a type name, a constructor name must start
      with a capital letter.)  Finally, the <type>Int</type> and
      <type>String</type> are the <emphasis>components</emphasis> of
      the type.  A component serves the same purpose in Haskell as a
      field in a structure or class would in another language.</para>

    <note>
      <title>Deriving what?</title>

      <para id="x_E4">We'll explain the full meaning of <code>deriving
	  (Show)</code> later, in
	<xref linkend="hs.typeclasses.wellknown.show"/>.  For now,
	it's enough to know that we need to tack this onto a type
	declaration so that &ghci; will automatically know how to
	print a value of this type.</para>
    </note>

    <para id="x_F4">We can create a new value of type <type>MyType</type> by
      treating <function>MyConstructor</function> as a function, and
      calling it with arguments of types <type>Int</type> and
      <type>String</type>.</para>

    &MyType.hs:myValue;

    <para id="x_G4">Once we've defined a type, we can experiment with it in
      &ghci;, starting by using the <command>:load</command> command
      to load our source file.</para>

    &mytype.ghci:load;


    <para id="x_H4">Remember the <code>myValue</code> variable we defined?  Here
      it is.</para>

    &mytype.ghci:myValue;

    <para>A constructor serves as both a function for creating a value
      and a <quote>tag</quote> identifying what type of value we have.
      The value that &ghci; prints is telling us that we have created
      a value with the tag <code>MyConstructor</code>, with the given
      values in each <quote>slot</quote>.  (By the way, this is why we
      had to add <code>deriving (Show)</code> to the definition of our
      type; without that, &ghci; would print an error message, telling
      us that it doesn't know how to print a value of this
      type.)</para>

    <para id="x_I4">We can construct new values interactively in &ghci;,
      too.</para>

    &mytype.ghci:newValue;

    <para>The &ghci; command <command>:type</command> lets us see what
      the type of that expression is.</para>

    &mytype.ghci:valueType;

    <para id="x_J4">To find out more about a type, we can use some of &ghci;'s
      browsing capabilities.  The <command>:info</command> command
      gets &ghci; to tell us everything it knows about a
      type.</para>
    
    &mytype.ghci:info;

    <para id="x_K4">We can also find out why we use
      <function>MyConstructor</function> to construct a new value of
      type <type>MyType</type>.</para>

    &mytype.ghci:type;

    <para id="x_L4">From Haskell's perspective, then, a constructor is just
      another function, one that happens to return a value of the type
      we want to construct.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.adt">
    <title>Algebraic data types</title>

    <para id="x_M4">The <type>Bool</type> type that we introduced earlier is the
      simplest example of a sort of type called an <emphasis>algebraic
	data type</emphasis>. An algebraic data type has a fixed set
      of possible values, each of which is identified by a distinct
      constructor.</para>

    <para>The use of the word <quote>algebraic</quote> simply
      indicates that the components of an algebraic data type are used
      together.</para>

    <para id="x_N4">In the case of <type>Bool</type>, the type has two
      constructors, <code>True</code> and <code>False</code>.  Each
      constructor is separated by a <literal>|</literal> character,
      which we can read as <quote>or</quote>.  These are usually
      referred to as alternatives or cases.</para>

      &Bool.hs:Bool;

    <para id="x_O4">Each constructor of an algebraic type can take
      zero or more arguments; the numbers and types of the arguments
      accepted by each constructor are independent.  For example,
      here's one way we might represent versions of the Windows
      operating system, where old releases were monolithic, and newer
      releases have <quote>service pack levels</quote> denoting major
      updates after their initial releases.</para>

      &OsVersion.hs:WindowsVersion;

    <para id="x_P4">The alternatives that represent older releases don't need
      arguments, but those for the newer releases need an
      <type>Int</type> to represent the patch level.</para>

    <sect2 id="hs.funcstypes.adt.comp">
      <title>Analogues to algebraic data types in other
	languages</title>

      <para id="x_Q4">Algebraic data types provide a single structuring
	mechanism in instances where other languages have several
	different building blocks.  Here are some analogues from C and
	C++, which might make it clearer what we can do with algebraic
	data types.</para>

      <para id="x_R4">With just one constructor, an algebraic data type groups
	related values into one, and gives that value an identity
	distinct from other types.  It corresponds to a
	<code>struct</code> in C or C++, and its components correspond to the
	fields of a struct.  Here's such a <code>struct</code>.</para>

      &types.c:coord;

      <para>And here's an equivalent type in Haskell.</para>

      &SimpleTypes.hs:Coord;

      <para>The only significant difference is that the fields in the
	Haskell type are anonymous and positional.  In <xref
	linkend="hs.funcstypes.pattern"/>, we'll see how to use names
	to access the fields of the <type>Coord</type> type.</para>

      <para id="x_S4">If an algebraic data type has multiple alternatives, we
	can think of it as similar to a <code>union</code> in C or
	C++.  A big difference between the two is that a union doesn't
	tell us which alternative is actually present; we have to
	record which alternative we're using ourselves, usually in
	another field of a struct.  This means that unions can
	sometimes be sources of bugs, where our notion of which
	alternative we should be using is incorrect.</para>

      <para id="x_T4">With an algebraic data type, Haskell stores the
	constructor that we use in the value that we create, so we
	don't need to manually sock it away somewhere else.</para>

      <para id="x_U4">Algebraic data types also serve where we'd use
	an <code>enum</code> in C or C++, to represent a range of
	discrete symbolic values. Such algebraic data types are
	sometimes referred to as enumeration types.  Here's an example
	from C.</para>

      &types.c:roygbiv;

      <para>And here's a Haskell equivalent.</para>

      &SimpleTypes.hs:Roygbiv;

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="hs.funcstypes.adt.notes">
      <title>A few final notes</title>

      <para id="x_V4">From reading the preceding sections, it should be clear
	that <emphasis>all</emphasis> of the data types that we define
	with the <code>data</code> keyword are algebraic data types.
	Some may have just one alternative; others have several; but
	they're all using the same organising machinery.</para>

      <para id="x_W4">Another useful thing to know is that it's perfectly okay
	for the name of an algebraic type to have the same name as one
	of its constructors to be the same.  It's always obvious from
	context whether we're using a name to refer to a type or a
	constructor, so this doesn't introduce any ambiguity.</para>

      <para id="x_X4">Giving a type and its constructor the same name is in fact
	something that we do frequently when the type has just one
	constructor.</para>

      &TypeName.hs:PerfectlyNormal;

      <para id="x_Y4">When a type has multiple constructors, it's still legal to
	give one of the constructors the  same name as the type, but
	this is much less common.</para>

      &TypeName.hs:LegalButWeird;

    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.paramtypes">
    <title>Parameterised types</title>

    <para id="x_Z4">In our discussion of lists, we mentioned that we can create
      a list of values of any type.  We can define our own types that
      allow this, too.  To do this, we introduce variables into a type
      declaration.</para>

      &Wrapper.hs:Wrapper;

    <para id="x_a4">Here, the variable <varname role="type">a</varname> is not a
      regular variable; it's called a <emphasis>type
	variable</emphasis>, because it indicates that our
      <type>Wrapper</type> type takes another type as its parameter
      (hence calling it a parameterised type). What this lets us do is
      use <type>Wrapper</type> on values of any type.</para>

      &Wrapper.hs:wrappedTypes;

    <para id="x_b4">As usual, we can load our source file into &ghci; and
      experiment with it.</para>

      &wrapper.ghci:experiment;

    <para id="x_c4"><type>Wrapper</type> is a <quote>generic</quote> container
      type (albeit a fairly useless one); we can construct a
      <type>Wrapper</type> from a value of any type.  It is also
      strongly typed; the type of whatever it contains is encoded in
      its own type.</para>

    <para id="x_d4">To once again extend an analogy to more familiar languages,
      this gives us a facility that bears some resemblance to
      templates in C++, and to generics in Java.  (In fact, Java's
      generics facility was inspired by several aspects of Haskell's
      type system.)</para>

    <para id="x_e4">We can nest uses of parameterised types inside each other,
      but when we do, we may need to use parentheses to tell the
      Haskell compiler what we mean.</para>

      &Wrapper.hs:parens;
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.locals">
    <title>Back to writing functions: local variables</title>

    <para id="x_f4">Let's take a break from writing about types for a few
      moments.  Within the body of a function, we can introduce new
      local variables whenever we need them, using a <code>let</code>
      expression.  As an example, let's write a function that
      calculates the real-valued roots of the quadratic equation
      <literal>a * (x ** 2) + b * x + c == 0</literal>.</para>

    &Roots.hs:realRoots;

    <para id="x_g4">The keywords to look out for here are <code>let</code>,
      which starts a block of variable declarations, and
      <code>in</code>, which ends it.  Each line introduces a new
      variable.  The name is on the left of the <literal>=</literal>,
      and its value on the right.  We can use these variables both
      within our block of variable declarations and in the expression
      that follows the <code>in</code> keyword.</para>

    <para id="x_h4">There's no problem with a variable earlier in a
      <code>let</code> block referring to a later one, or even with
      them referring to each other.  (In some functional languages,
      this sort of flexible <code>let</code> is named
      <code>letrec</code>.)</para>

    <para id="x_i4">We can have multiple <code>let</code> blocks within an
      expression.  There's also another mechanism we can use to
      introduce local variables, called a <code>where</code> block.
      The definitions in a <code>where</code> block apply to the code
      that <emphasis>precedes</emphasis> it.  Let's illustrate what we
      mean with another example.</para>

    &Roots.hs:roots;

    <para id="x_j4">Here, the <function>roots</function> function returns the
      real roots when they're defined, and the complex roots
      otherwise. (We left out the divide-by-zero case for simplicity.)
      While a <quote>where</quote> clause initially looks very weird
      to non-Haskell programmers, it's a great way to put the
      <quote>important</quote> code early, followed by the auxiliary
      definitions that support it.  After a while, you'll find
      yourself missing <code>where</code> clauses in languages that
      lack them!</para>

    <para id="x_k4">The main difference between <code>let</code> and
      <code>where</code> is one of scope.  The scope of a
      <code>let</code> only extends to the expression after the
      <code>in</code> keyword, while the variables introduced by a
      <code>where</code> clause are visible upwards to the beginning
      of the block that it <quote>belongs</quote> to. Also,
      <code>let</code> is always paired with an expression, but
      <code>where</code> is paired with a block of equations.</para>

    <para id="x_l4">We'll be talking more about how to write <code>let</code>
      expressions and <code>where</code> clauses in <xref
	linkend="hs.funcstypes.offside"/>.</para>

    <note>
      <title>A few observations about complex numbers</title>

      <para id="x_m4">It's probably obvious from context above, but
	<function>(:+)</function> is the constructor for a complex
	number, taking the real part on the left and the imaginary
	part on the right.</para>

      <para id="x_n4">Also, <type>Complex</type> is parameterised over the type
	of complex number it should represent.  In practice, it only
	makes much sense to use <type>Complex Double</type>, since
	&GHC; implements <type>Double</type> more efficiently than
	<type>Float</type>.</para>
    </note>

    <sect2 id="hs.funcstypes.locals.functions">
      <title>Local functions</title>

      <para>You'll have noticed that Haskell's syntax for defining a
	variable looks very similar to its syntax for defining a
	function.  This symmetry is preserved in <code>let</code> and
	<code>where</code> blocks; we can define local
	<emphasis>functions</emphasis> just as easily as local
	<emphasis>variables</emphasis>.  All of the same syntax
	applies as at the top level: we can use multiple equations,
	patterns, and guards.</para>

      &LocalFunction.hs:pluralise;

      <para>In this example, we define and use a local function
	<function>plural</function> using several equations.  Local
	functions can freely use variables from the scopes that
	enclose them; here, we use <varname>word</varname> from the
	definition of the outer function
	<function>pluralise</function>.  In the definition of
	<function>pluralise</function>, the <function>map</function>
	function (which we'll be revisiting in the next chapter)
	applies the local function <function>plural</function> to
	every element of the <varname>counts</varname> list.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.maybe">
    <title>How to represent a complicated result</title>

    <para id="x_o4">We sneaked two previously unseen standard types,
      <type>Maybe</type> and <type>Either</type>, into our
      root-finding examples.  We use <type>Maybe</type> when it might
      not make sense to return a normal result, for example because a
      function's result is undefined for some inputs.  We use
      <function>Just</function> to say <quote>we have a
	result</quote>, and the argument to <function>Just</function>
      is that result.  When we can't give a result, we use
      <function>Nothing</function>, which takes no arguments.</para>

    &realRoots.ghci:maybe;
    
    <para id="x_p4">Why do we need <type>Maybe</type> here?  The real-valued
      roots of a quadratic equation are infinity when
      <varname>a</varname>, the coefficient of <literal>x **
	2</literal>, is zero.</para>

    &realRoots.ghci:a0;

    <para id="x_q4">They're also not defined when <literal>b ** 2 - 4 * a *
	c</literal> is negative, because we would need to use complex
      numbers to represent a negative square root.</para>

    &realRoots.ghci:complex;

    <para id="x_r4">Otherwise, we can return a normal result, wrapped in
      <function>Just</function>.</para>

    &realRoots.ghci:just;

    <para id="x_s4">Compared to <function>error</function>, which we saw in
      <xref linkend="hs.funcstypes.error"/>, <type>Maybe</type> has
      the huge advantage that it's a normal value, which we return to
      our caller to deal with.  Calling <function>error</function>, by
      contrast, is more akin to pulling on the program's ejector seat
      handle as it disintegrates around us; something terrible has
      happened, and we need to give up right now.</para>

    <para id="x_t4">The <type>Either a b</type> type gives us even more
      flexibility than <type>Maybe</type>, as it's got two type
      parameters. We can wrap a value of any type <varname
	role="type">a</varname> with <type>Left</type>, or a value of
      an unrelated type <varname role="type">b</varname> with
      <type>Right</type>.  Our <function>roots</function> function
      uses this to return a <type>Double</type> when the real roots
      are defined, and a <type>Complex Double</type> when they're
      not.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.offside">
    <title>The offside rule, and white space in a function
      body</title>

    <para id="x_u4">In our definition of <function>realRoots</function>, the
      left margin of our text wandered around quite a bit.  This was
      not an accident: in Haskell, white space has meaning.</para>

    <para id="x_v4">Haskell uses indentation as a cue to parse sections of code.
      This use of layout to convey structure is sometimes called the
      offside rule. At the top level, the first declaration or
      definition can start in any column, and the Haskell compiler or
      interpreter remembers that indentation level.  Every subsequent
      top-level declaration must have the same indentation.</para>

    <para id="x_w4">Here's an illustration of the top-level indentation rule.
      Our first file, <filename>GoodIndent.hs</filename>, is well
      behaved.</para>

    &GoodIndent.hs:good;

    <para id="x_x4">Our second, <filename>BadIndent.hs</filename>, doesn't play
      by the rules.</para>

    &BadIndent.hs:bad;

    <para id="x_y4">Here's what happens when we try to load the two files into
      &ghci;.</para>

    &indent.ghci:load;

    <para id="x_z4">An empty line is treated as a continuation of the current
      item, as is a line indented to the right of the current current
      item.</para>

    <para id="x_A5">The rules for <code>let</code> expressions and
      <code>where</code> clauses are similar.  After a
      <code>let</code> or <code>where</code> keyword, the Haskell
      compiler or interpreter remembers the indentation of the next
      token it sees. If the next line is empty, or its indentation is
      further to the right than the previous line, this counts as
      continuing the previous line. On the other hand, if the
      indentation is the same as the previous line, this is treated as
      beginning a new item in the same block.</para>

    <para id="x_B5">Here are nested uses of <code>let</code> and
      <code>where</code>.</para>

    &letwhere.hs:let;

    <para id="x_C5">In the body of <varname>bar</varname>, the variable
      <varname>a</varname> is only visible within the <code>let</code>
      expression that defines it.  It's not visible to the
      <code>let</code> expression that defines <varname>b</varname>;
      only the <emphasis>result</emphasis> of the inner
      <code>let</code> expression is visible.</para>

    &letwhere.hs:where;

    <para id="x_D5">Similarly, the scope of the first <code>where</code> clause
      is the definition of <varname>foo</varname>, but the scope of
      the second is just the first <code>where</code> clause.</para>

    <para id="x_E5">The indentation we use for the <code>let</code> and
      <code>where</code> clauses makes our intentions easy to figure
      out.</para>

    <sect2 id="hs.funcstypes.tabs">
      <title>A note about tabs versus spaces</title>

      <para id="x_F5">If you are using a Haskell-aware text editor (e.g. Emacs),
	it is probably already configured to use space characters for
	all white space within a line.  If your editor is
	<emphasis>not</emphasis> Haskell-aware, you should configure
	it to only use space characters.</para>

      <para id="x_G5">The reason for this is simple portability.  In an editor
	that uses a fixed-width font, tab stops are by default placed
	at different intervals on Unix-like systems (every eight
	characters) than on Windows  (every four characters). This
	means that no matter what your personal beliefs are about
	where tabs belong, you can't rely on someone else's editor
	honouring your preferences.  Any indentation that uses tabs is
	going to look broken under <emphasis>someone's</emphasis>
	configuration; this could lead to compilation problems, too.
	Using space characters instead avoids this problem
	entirely.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="hs.funcstypes.block">
      <title>The offside rule is not mandatory</title>

      <para id="x_H5">We can use explicit structuring instead of layout to
	indicate what we mean.  To do so, we start a block of
	equations with an opening curly brace; separate each item with
	a semicolon; and finish the block with a closing curly brace.
	The following two uses of <code>let</code> have the same
	meanings.</para>

      &Braces.hs:braces;

      <para id="x_I5">When we use explicit structuring, the normal layout rules
	don't apply, which is why we can get away with unusual
	indentation in the second <code>let</code> expression.</para>

      <para id="x_J5">We can use explicit structuring anywhere that we'd
	normally use layout.  It's valid for <code>where</code>
	clauses, and even top-level declarations.  Just remember that
	although the facility exists, explicit structuring is hardly
	ever actually <emphasis>used</emphasis> in Haskell
	programs.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.recursive">
    <title>Recursive types</title>

    <para id="x_K5">Here's a definition of a binary tree type.</para>

      &Tree.hs:Tree;

    <para id="x_L5">We call this a <emphasis>recursive</emphasis> type because
      <type>Tree</type>, the type we're defining, appears both on the
      left hand side and the right hand side of the definition: we
      define the type in terms of itself.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.listadt">
    <title>A little more about lists</title>

    <para id="x_M5">Now that we're getting familiar with some of the jargon
      around types, we can revisit lists.  Haskell's list type is a
      parameterised type, because we can make lists of any other type.
      It is also an algebraic data type, with two constructors.  One
      is the empty list, written <code>[]</code> (sometimes pronounced
      <quote>nil</quote>, which is borrowed from Lisp).</para>

    &list.ghci:empty;

    <para id="x_N5">The other is the <function>(:)</function> operator, often
      pronounced <quote>cons</quote> (this is short for
      <quote>construct</quote>, and also borrowed from Lisp).  The
      <function>(:)</function> operator takes an element and a list,
      and constructs a new list.</para>

    &list.ghci:cons;

    <para id="x_O5">We can use <function>(:)</function> repeatedly to add new
      elements to the front of a list.</para>

    &list.ghci:cons2;

    <para id="x_P5">The right hand side of <function>(:)</function> must be a
      list, and of the correct type.  If it's not, we'll get an
      error.</para>

    &list.ghci:cons.bad;

    <para id="x_Q5">Because <function>(:)</function> constructs a list from
      another list, the list type is recursive.  So here we have a
      built-in type that's parameterised, recursive, and
      algebraic.</para>

    <para id="x_R5">One consequence of lists being generic is that lists of
      lists, for example, aren't special in any way.</para>

    &list.ghci:listlist;

    <para id="x_S5">This has type <type>[[String]]</type>, a list of lists of
      strings.  But since <type>String</type> is just a synonym for
      <type>[Char]</type>, it's <emphasis>really</emphasis> a list of
      lists of lists of <type>Char</type>.  Whew!</para>

    <para id="x_T5">We're not limited to building up lists one element at a
      time.  Haskell defines an inline function,
      <function>(++)</function>, that we can use to append one list
      onto the end of another.</para>

    &list.ghci:append;

    <para id="x_U5">The <function>concat</function> function takes a list of
      lists, and concatenates the whole lot into a single list.</para>

    &list.ghci:concat;

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.unit">
    <title>Unit, the zero-element tuple</title>

    <para id="x_V5">Haskell has a special tuple type with no elements, written
      <type>()</type>, and pronounced <quote>unit</quote>.</para>

    &unit.ghci:unit;

    <para id="x_W5">This type is only really used with parameterised data types,
      to indicate that one of the type parameters isn't being used.
      Since it doesn't encode any information, it's a rough equivalent
      to <code>void</code> in C.</para>

    <para id="x_X5">Here's an example of <type>()</type> in use.  We can
      generalise our earlier <type>Tree</type> type a little, so that
      internal nodes contain values of type <varname
	role="type">a</varname>, while leaves contain values of type
      <varname role="type">b</varname>.</para>

    &Tree.hs:ComplexTree;

    <para id="x_Y5">If we wanted to create a <type>ComplexTree</type> where we
      wanted to store <type>Int</type>s on the leaves, but don't care
      about the internal nodes.  We would write its type as
      <type>ComplexTree () Int</type>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.pattern">
    <title>Pattern matching</title>

    <para id="x_Z5">Although we introduced a handful of functions earlier that
      can operate on lists, we've yet to see how we might generally
      get values out of a constructed algebraic data type.  Haskell
      has a simple pattern matching facility that we can use to this
      end.</para>

    <para id="x_a5">A pattern lets us peer inside a compound value and bind
      variables to the values it contains.  In fact, when we define a
      function, the parameters to that function are really patterns
      that bind our variables to an entire value.</para>

    <para id="x_b5">Here's an example of pattern matching in action on a list;
      we're going to add all elements of the list together.</para>

    &add.hs:sumList;

    <para id="x_c5">See that <code>(x:xs)</code> on the left of the first line?
      The <code>:</code> means <quote>match the head of a
	list</quote>; that's the familiar list constructor,
      <function>(:)</function>, in action in a new way.  The variables
      <varname>x</varname> and <varname>xs</varname> are given the
      values of (<quote>bound to</quote>) the head and tail of the
      list, respectively.  The whole pattern is wrapped in parentheses
      so Haskell won't parse it as three separate arguments.</para>

    <para id="x_d5">What effect does pattern matching have? Haskell will only
      evaluate the right hand side of an equation if it can match all
      of the patterns on the left hand side.  In the definition of
      <function>sumList</function> above, the right hand side of the
      first equation won't be evaluated if the input list is empty.
      Instead, Haskell will <quote>fall through</quote> to the
      equation on the following line, which <emphasis>does</emphasis>
      have a pattern for the empty list, and it will evaluate
      that.</para>

    <para id="x_e5">It might initially look like we have two functions
      named <function>sumList</function> here, but Haskell lets us
      define a function as a series of equations; so in fact these two
      clauses are defining the behaviour of one function, over
      different inputs.  (By the way, there's already a standard
      function, <function>sum</function>, that does this
      adding-of-a-list for us.  This <function>sumList</function> is
      purely for illustration.)</para>

    <para id="x_f5">The syntax for pattern matching on a tuple is similar to the
      syntax for constructing a tuple.  Here's a function that returns
      the third element from a three-tuple.</para>

    &Tuple.hs:third;

    <para id="x_g5">There's no limit on how <quote>deep</quote> within a value a
      pattern can look.  Here's a definition that looks both inside a
      tuple and inside a list within that tuple.</para>

    &Tuple.hs:complicated;

    <para id="x_h5">We can try this out interactively.</para>

    &tuple.ghci:complicated;

    <para id="x_i5">Wherever a literal value is present in a pattern
      (<literal>True</literal> and <literal>5</literal> in the tuple
      pattern above), that value must match exactly for the pattern
      match to succeed.  If every pattern within a series of equations
      fails to match, we get a runtime error.</para>

    &tuple.ghci:nomatch;

    <para id="x_j5">We can pattern match on algebraic data types using their
      constructors.  Remember the <type>Wrapper</type> type we defined
      earlier?  Here's how we can extract a wrapped value from a
      <type>Wrapper</type>.</para>

    &Wrapper.hs:unwrap;

    <para id="x_k5">Let's see it in action.</para>

    &wrapper.ghci:unwrap;

    <para id="x_l5">Notice that Haskell infers the type of the
      <function>unwrap</function> function based on the constructor
      we're using in our pattern.  If we're trying to match a value
      whose constructor is <function>Wrapper</function>, then the type
      of that parameter must be <type>Wrapper a</type>.</para>
    
    <para>And for good measure, here's how we can define functions to
      access the fields of the <type>Coord</type> type we defined in
      <xref linkend="hs.funcstypes.adt.comp"/>.</para>

    &SimpleTypes.hs:accessors;

    <note>
      <title>The ordering of patterns is important</title>

      <para id="x_m5">Haskell tests patterns for matches in the order in which
	we list them in our code.  It goes from top to bottom and
	stops at the first match; it <emphasis>does not</emphasis>
	check every pattern and use the best match.</para>

      <para id="x_n5">If you're familiar with pattern matching from a logic
	programming language like Prolog, Haskell's facility is
	simpler and less powerful.  It doesn't provide backtracking or
	unification.</para>
    </note>

    <para>Here are some rules of thumb to help with remembering how
      pattern matching works.  A constructor in a pattern
      checks that the matched value has the right <quote>shape</quote>.  A
      literal value ensures that that portion of the value has exactly
      the matching contents.  And a variable makes no assertions about
      either the shape or contents of the matched value; it matches anything,
      and gives the variable that value.</para>

    <para>So the pattern <code>(3:xs)</code> first of all is an
      assertion that a matching value is a non-empty list, by matching
      against the <function>(:)</function> constructor.  It also
      ensures that the head of the list is the literal value
      <literal>3</literal>.  And whatever the tail of the list is, it
      will be bound to the variable <varname>xs</varname>.</para>

    <sect2 id="hs.funcstypes.dontcare">
      <title>The don't-care, or wild card, pattern</title>

      <para id="x_o5">When we're writing a pattern, we can specify that we don't
	care what value a particular value within a structure has,
	without actually binding that value to a name.  The notation
	for this is <code>_</code> (called a wild card or <quote>don't
	  care</quote>), and we use it as follows.  This function
	tells us whether the result of the <function>roots</function>
	function we defined earlier is real-valued or not.</para>

      &Roots.hs:isRealValued;

      <para id="x_p5">Here, we don't care about the value of the result, just
	about which constructor was used to create it.  If it was
	<function>Left</function>, the result must be a complex
	number, otherwise it must be real.  We can use a wild card for
	the entire second pattern; there's no need to see if the
	constructor is <function>Right</function>, because it
	<emphasis>must</emphasis> be; <type>Either</type> only has two
	constructors.</para>

      <para>In a pattern, a wild card acts similarly
	to a variable, only it doesn't bind the value to a name.
	While we can't put the same variable name multiple times in a
	single pattern, we can use a wild card as many times as we
	need to.</para>

      <para>Another advantage of wild cards is that a Haskell compiler
	can warn us if we introduce a variable name in a pattern, but
	don't use it in a function's body; defining something but
	forgetting to use it can often indicate a bug.  Using a wild
	card instead of an unused variable makes it explicit that we
	really don't care what value is present, and will prevent such
	a warning.</para>

      <para>Wild cards also help readability, as they make it easier
	to tell which values we're really using.</para>

      &SimpleTypes.hs:niceAccessors;

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="hs.funcstypes.case">
      <title>The case expression</title>

      <para id="x_q5">We're not limited to using patterns in function
	definitions.  The <code>case</code> expression lets us match
	patterns at any time.  Here's what it looks like.</para>

      &Roots.hs:hasRealRoots;

      <para id="x_r5">The <code>case</code> keyword is followed by an arbitrary
	expression; the result of this expression is what we're
	pattern matching on.  The <code>of</code> keyword signifies
	the end of the expression and the beginning of the block of
	patterns and expressions.</para>

      <para id="x_s5">Each item in the block consists of a pattern, followed by
	an arrow <code>-&gt;</code>, followed by an expression to
	evaluate if that pattern matches.  The result of the
	<code>case</code> expression is the result of the expression
	associated with the first pattern to match, taken from top to
	bottom.</para>

      <para id="x_t5">To express <quote>here's the expression to evaluate if
	  none of the other patterns match</quote>, we would just use
	the wild card pattern <code>_</code> as the last in our list
	of patterns.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="hs.funcstypes.where">
      <title>A flying visit back to the where clause</title>

      <para id="x_u5">Now that we've seen that we can define a function as a
	series of equations, the usefulness of the <code>where</code>
	clause should be a bit more clear.  Variables that we define
	inside a <code>where</code> clause are visible across all of
	the equations that precede it in a single block.</para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="hs.funcstypes.pattern.limits">
      <title>Early pattern matching pitfalls</title>

      <para>There are a few ways in which new Haskell programmers can
	misunderstand or misuse patterns.  Here are a few potential
	missteps that you can easily avoid.</para>

      <para id="x_v5">There's no way to write a pattern that compares
	a value with a variable.  Matching a pattern only lets us
	perform exact comparisons against combinations of constructors
	and simple values.</para>

      <para>Here's a well-intentioned example of pattern matching gone
	awry.  This code compiles cleanly, but depending on what you
	expect it to do, it might surprise you.</para>

      &BogusPattern.hs:isHead;

      <para id="x_w5">A naive glance suggests that this code is trying
	to check the value of <function>f</function> to see if it's
	actually the standard function <function>head</function>, but
	here's what it is <emphasis>really</emphasis> doing.</para>

      <para id="x_x5">Because the first pattern in the
	<code>case</code> expression is a variable, this branch of the
	<code>case</code> will <emphasis>always</emphasis> match, no
	matter what the value of <varname>f</varname> is.  The name
	<varname>head</varname> thus acts as a local variable whose
	value is the value of <varname>f</varname>, which hides the
	global definition of the well-known <function>head</function>
	function.  </para>

      <note>
	<title>Irrefutable patterns</title>

	<para id="x_y5">A pattern that consists only of a variable will always
	  match, because it's not being compared against any value that
	  could cause the match to fail.  We refer to patterns that
	  always match as <quote>irrefutable</quote>.</para>
      </note>

      <para id="x_z5">The first pattern always matches, because it's
	irrefutable.  But the second pattern <emphasis>also</emphasis>
	always matches, because it uses a wild card.  However, because
	Haskell attempts to match patterns in the order in which we
	write them, the first pattern will always succeed, and the
	second pattern will never actually be reached. Because the two
	patterns will match the same values, they are said to
	<emphasis>overlap</emphasis>.  If &GHC; ever complains to you
	about overlapping patterns, it's telling you that one of your
	patterns is the same as another, and so it will never actually
	be matched.</para>

      <para id="x_A6">Another thing to be aware of is that a variable
	can only appear once in a pattern.  For example, we can't put
	a variable in multiple places within a pattern to express the
	notion <quote>this value and that should be
	  identical</quote>.</para>

      <para id="x_B6">The way around these restrictions of Haskell's patterns is
	to use patterns in combination with a language facility called
	<emphasis>guards</emphasis>, which we'll talk about
	next.</para>

    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.guard">
    <title>Conditional evaluation with guards</title>

    <para id="x_C6">We can further extend our expressive arsenal using
      <emphasis>guards</emphasis>.  A guard is an expression of type
      <type>Bool</type>; if it evaluates to <function>True</function>,
      the equation that follows it is evaluated.  Otherwise, the next
      guard in the series is evaluated, and so on.  A series of guards
      is only checked if the patterns that they're associated with
      match.  Here's an example of guards in action.</para>

    &Roots.hs:guardedRoots;

    <para id="x_D6">Each guard is introduced by a <code>|</code> symbol,
      followed by the guard expression, then an <code>=</code> symbol
      (or <code>-&gt;</code> if within a <code>case</code>
      expression), then the expression to evaluate if the guard
      succeeds.  A guard expression can use any variables matched in
      the pattern that precedes it.</para>

    <para id="x_E6">The <varname>otherwise</varname> used in the second guard
      has an obvious meaning: it's the expression to evaluate if
      previous gaurds all evaluate to <function>False</function>. It's
      not a special piece of syntax, though; it's just a predefined variable
      whose value is <function>True</function>.</para>

    <para id="x_F6">We can use guards anywhere that we can use
      patterns.  The advantage of writing a function as a series of
      equations using pattern matching and guards is that it often
      makes code much clearer.  Remember the
      <function>myTake</function> function we defined in <xref
	linkend="hs.funcstypes.if"/>?</para>

    &myTake.hs:myTake.noid;

    <para id="x_H6">Here's a reformulation of that function using
      patterns and guards.  Instead of reasoning about what an
      <code>if</code> expression is doing and which branch will be
      evaluated, the code uses a series of equations with simple
      patterns and guards. Hoisting the control decisions to the
      <quote>outside</quote> of the code, instead of burying it inside
      with <code>if</code> expressions, lets us enumerate up front
      the cases in which we expect the behaviour of the function to
      differ.</para>

    &myTake.hs:niceTake;

    <para id="x_I6">Let's return to one of the limitations of patterns that we
      mentioned in the previous section: the fact that we can't 
      check two variables within a pattern for equality.
      We can express this quite easily by following the pattern with a
      guard.</para>

    &Guard.hs:secondEqualsThird;

    <para id="x_J6">Here, for good measure, we've illustrated guard
      syntax in a <code>case</code> expression.  This guard expression
      compares the variables matched in the pattern for equality.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.infix">
    <title>Infix functions</title>

    <para id="x_K6">Usually, when we define or call a function in Haskell, we
      write the name of the function, followed by its arguments; this
      is called prefix notation, because the name of the function
      comes before its arguments.  For a function that takes two
      arguments, we have the option of using it in
      <emphasis>infix</emphasis> form, between its first and second
      arguments.  This allows us to write expressions using functions
      as if they were infix operators.</para>

    <para id="x_L6">The syntax for defining or calling a function in infix form
      is to enclose the name of the function in backtick characters
      (sometimes known as backquotes).  Here's a simple infix
      definition.</para>

    &Plus.hs:plus;

    <para id="x_M6">Defining a function in infix form doesn't change anything
      about the behaviour of the function.  We can call the function
      using infix or prefix notation, as we prefer.</para>

    &infix.ghci:plus;

    <para id="x_N6">Infix notation is useful for more than just our own
      functions.  For example, Haskell's standard
      <code>Data.List</code> module defines a function,
      <function>isPrefixOf</function>, that indicates whether all
      elements of its first argument are equal to the first elements
      of its second argument.</para>

    &infix.ghci:type;

    <para id="x_O6">Let's define a few variables in &ghci;.</para>

    &infix.ghci:vars;

    <para id="x_P6">If we call <function>isPrefixOf</function> using prefix
      notation, we can have a hard time remembering which argument
      we're checking for as a prefix of the other.</para>

    &infix.ghci:prefix;

    <para id="x_Q6">But if we use infix notation, the code <quote>reads</quote>
      more naturally; it's now obvious that we're checking the
      variable on the left to see if it's a prefix of the variable on
      the right.</para>

    &infix.ghci:infix;

    <para id="x_R6">There's no hard-and-fast rule that dictates when you ought
      to use infix versus prefix notation, although prefix notation is
      far more common.  It's best to choose whichever makes your code
      more readable in a specific situation.</para>

    <note>
      <para id="x_S6">The backtick notation is not a general mechanism: it's a
	piece of special syntax that applies only to names.  For
	example, we can't put backticks around an expression that
	returns a function, and then treat that as an infix
	function.</para>
    </note>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hs.funcstypes.end">
    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para id="x_T6">In this chapter, we've had a whirlwind overview of Haskell's
      type system and much of its syntax.  We've read about basic
      types, compound types, and how to write our own algebraic data
      types.  We've seen how to write functions, and how to declare
      local variables within them.  We've read about Haskell's offside
      rule for laying out functions, and how we can avoid it if we
      need to.  We've seen conditional evaluation, pattern matching
      and guards.  We've discussed error handling.</para>

    <para id="x_U6">This all amounts to a lot of information to absorb.  In
      <xref linkend="hs.fp"/>, we'll build on this basic knowledge to
      understand how we can write, and think about, code in
      Haskell.</para>

  </sect1>

</chapter>
<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("00book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
