<!-- vim: set filetype=docbkxml shiftwidth=2 autoindent expandtab tw=77 : -->

<chapter id="gui" revision="unpublished">
  <title>GUI Programming with gtk2hs</title>
  <para>
    Thoughout this book, we have been developing simple text-based
    tools.  While these are often ideal interfaces, sometimes a
    graphical user interface (GUI) is required.  There are several GUI
    toolkits available for Haskell.  In this chapter, we will look at
    the most popular of them, gtk2hs.
  </para>
  
  <sect1 id="gui.install">
    <title>Installing gtk2hs</title>
    <para>
      Before we dive in to working with gtk2hs, you'll need to get it
      installed.  On most Linux, BSD, or other POSIX platforms, you
      will find ready-made gtk2hs packages.  You will generally need
      to install the GTK+ devlopment environment, glade, and gtk2hs.
      The specifics of doing so vary by distribution.
    </para>
    <para>
      Windows and Mac developers should consult the gtk2hs downloads
      site at <ulink
      url="http://www.haskell.org/gtk2hs/download/"></ulink>.  Begin
      by downloading gtk2hs from there.  Then you will also need glade
      version 3.  Mac developers can find this at <ulink
      url="http://www.macports.org/"></ulink>, while Windows
      developers should consult <ulink
      url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/gladewin32"></ulink>.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gui.overview">
    <title>Overview of the GTK+ Stack</title>
    <para>
      Before diving in to the code, let's pause a brief moment and
      consider the architecture of the system we are going to use.
      First off, we have GTK+.  GTK+ is a cross-platform GUI-building
      toolkit, implemented in C.  It runs on Windows, Mac, Linux,
      BSDs, and more.  It is also the toolkit beneath the Gnome
      desktop environment.
    </para>
    <para>
      Next, we have Glade.  Glade is a user interface designer, which
      lets you graphically lay out your application's windows and
      dialogs.  Glade saves the interface in XML files, which your
      application will load at runtime.
    </para>
    <para>
      The last piece of this puzzle is gtk2hs.  This is the Haskell
      binding for GTK+, Glade, and several related libraries.  It is
      one of many language bindings available for GTK+.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gui.steps">
    <title>First Steps</title>
    <para>
      In this chapter, we are going to develop a GUI for the podcast
      downloader we first developed in <xref linkend="wc"/>.  Our
      first task is to design the user interface in Glade.  Once we
      have accomplished that, we will write the Haskell code to
      integrate it with the application.
    </para>
    <para>
      Because this is a Haskell book, rather than a GUI design book,
      we will move fast through some of these early parts.  For more
      information on interface design with Glade, you may wish to
      refer to one of these resources:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>The Glade homepage, which contains documentation
      for Glade.  <ulink url="http://glade.gnome.org/"></ulink>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>The GTK+ homepage contains information about the
      different widgets.  Refer to the documentation section, then the
      stable GTK documentation area.  <ulink
      url="http://www.gtk.org/"></ulink>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>
          The gtk2hs homepage also has a useful documentation section,
          which contains an API reference to gtk2hs as well as a glade
          tutorial.  <ulink
          url="http://www.haskell.org/gtk2hs/"></ulink>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("00book.xml" "book" "chapter")
end:
-->
